How do you feed a city?
كيف تُطعم مدينة؟
It's one of the great questions of our time.
إنه واحد من أعظم الأسئلة في زماننا.
Yet it's one that's rarely asked.
مع أنه نادراً ما يُسأل
We take it for granted that if we go into a shop
نحن نعتبر أنه أمر مفروغ منه أن نذهب إلى متجر
or restaurant, or indeed into this theater's foyer in about an hour's time,
أو مطعم, أو إلى بهو هذا المسرح في غضون ساعة تقريبا
there is going to be food there waiting for us,
سيكون هناك طعام ينتظرنا
having magically come from somewhere.
جاء بطريقة سحرية من مكان ما.
But when you think that every day for a city the size of London,
لكن تخيل أنه يومياً في مدينة بمساحة لندن
enough food has to be produced,
كمية كافية من الغذاء يجب أن تُنتَج,
transported, bought and sold,
تُنقل,تُشترى و تُباع,
cooked, eaten, disposed of,
تُطبخ, تُؤكل, تُتلف,
and that something similar has to happen every day
و أشياء من هذا القبيل يجب أن تحدث يومياً
for every city on earth,
في كل مدينة على وجه الأرض
it's remarkable that cities get fed at all.
إطعام المدن شيء غير عادي أبداً.
We live in places like this as if
نحن نعيش في أماكن كتلك
they're the most natural things in the world,
وكأنهم الأشياء الأكثر طبيعيةً في العالم
forgetting that because we're animals
متناسين بأنه لأننا حيوانات
and that we need to eat,
و بأننا نحتاج أن نأكل
we're actually as dependent on the natural world
نحن في الواقع معتمدين على عالم الطبيعة
as our ancient ancestors were.
كما كان أجدادنا القدماء
And as more of us move into cities,
و لأن الكثيرين منا ينتقلون إلى المدن
more of that natural world is being
جزء كبير من عالم الطبيعة
transformed into extraordinary landscapes like the one behind me --
تغير إلى مناظر طبيعية غريبة كالذي خلفي
it's soybean fields in Mato Grosso in Brazil --
إنها حقول فول الصويا في ماتو غروسو في البرازيل
in order to feed us.
حتى يطعموننا
These are extraordinary landscapes,
هذه هي المناظر الطبيعية الغريبة.
but few of us ever get to see them.
لكن قليلين منا قاموا برؤيتها
And increasingly these landscapes
و بشكل متزايد هذه المناظر الطبيعية
are not just feeding us either.
لا تقوم بإطعامنا نحن فقط.
As more of us move into cities,
مع تزايد إنتقالنا إلى المدن,
more of us are eating meat,
أصبح الكثير منا يأكلون اللحم.
so that a third of the annual grain crop globally
و بالتالي ثلث محصول الحبوب السنوي عالمياً
now gets fed to animals
يذهب الآن لإطعام الحيوانات
rather than to us human animals.
بدلاً منا نحن الحيوانات البشرية
And given that it takes three times as much grain --
و على فرض أننا بحاجة إلى ثلاثة أضعاف كمية الحبوب -
actually ten times as much grain --
في الواقع عشرة أضعاف كمية الحبوب -
to feed a human if it's passed through an animal first,
لإطعامنا إذا مرت عن طريق حيوان إبتداءاً.
that's not a very efficient way of feeding us.
فهذه ليست طريقة فعّالة لإطعامنا.
And it's an escalating problem too.
و هذه مشكلة متصاعدة أيضاً.
By 2050, it's estimated that twice the number
من المتوقع أنه في 2050 ضعف عددنا
of us are going to be living in cities.
سيعيشون في المدن
And it's also estimated that there is going to be twice as much
و من متوقع أنه سيكون هناك ضعف
meat and dairy consumed.
الحاجة إلى اللحوم و الألبان
So meat and urbanism are rising hand in hand.
لذلك فإن اللحم و التمدن يتصاعدان يداً بيد
And that's going to pose an enormous problem.
و هذا سيطرح مشكلة كبيرة
Six billion hungry carnivores to feed,
إطعام سته مليار جائع آكل للحوم
by 2050.
في 2050
That's a big problem. And actually if we carry on as we are,
هذه مشكلة كبيرة. و في الواقع إذا إستمرينا على هذا النحو
it's a problem we're very unlikely to be able to solve.
هذه مشكلة قد لا نستطيع حلها.
Nineteen million hectares of rainforest are lost every year
19 مليون هكتار من الغابات المطرية تُفقَد سنويا
to create new arable land.
لإنشاء أراضي صالحة للزراعة.
Although at the same time we're losing an equivalent amount
مع أننا في ذات الوقت نفقد كمية مساوية
of existing arables to salinization and erosion.
من الأراضي الصالحة للزراعة بفعل التصحر و التعرية.
We're very hungry for fossil fuels too.
نحن جائعون جداً للوقود الأحفوري أيضاً.
It takes about 10 calories to produce every calorie
نحتاج إلى 10 سعرات حرارية تقريبا لإنتاج كل سعر حراري
of food that we consume in the West.
من الغذاء الذي نستهلكه في الغرب
And even though there is food that we are producing at great cost,
و بالرغم من أن هناك غذاء ننتجه بتكلفة كبيرة
we don't actually value it.
نحن في الواقع لا نقدره
Half the food produced in the USA is currently thrown away.
نصف الغذاء المُنتج في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية حالياً مُهمل
And to end all of this, at the end of this long process,
و لإنهاء كل ذلك, في نهاية هذه العملية الطويلة,
we're not even managing to feed the planet properly.
نحن حتى لا نقوم بإدارة التغذية بشكل صحيح
A billion of us are obese, while a further billion starve.
مليارٌ منا بدينون, و في ذات الوقت مليارٌ آخرون جائعون
None of it makes very much sense.
لا شيء منطقي في ذلك
And when you think that 80 percent of global trade in food now
و عندما تفكر في أن 80 بالمئة من التجارة العالمية بالغذاء الآن
is controlled by just five multinational corporations,
هي في يد خمس شركات عالمية فقط ,
it's a grim picture.
إنها صورة مُحبطة.
As we're moving into cities, the world is also embracing a Western diet.
و فيما نحن ننتقل إلى المدن, العالم أيضاً يعتنق نظاماً غذائياً غربي
And if we look to the future,
و إذا نظرنا إلى المستقبل
it's an unsustainable diet.
إنه نظام لا يمكن تحمله
So how did we get here?
إذاً كيف وصلنا إلى هنا؟
And more importantly, what are we going to do about it?
و الأهم, ماذا سنفعل حيال الأمر ؟
Well, to answer the slightly easier question first,
حسناً, للإجابة أولاً عن السؤال الأسهل
about 10,000 years ago, I would say,
قبل حوالي 10,000 سنة , سأقول
is the beginning of this process
أنه بداية هذه العملية.
in the ancient Near East,
في الشرق الأقرب القديم
known as the Fertile Crescent.
المعروف بالهلال الخصيب
Because, as you can see, it was crescent shaped.
لأنه كما ترون هلالي الشكل
And it was also fertile.
و أيضاً هو خصب
And it was here, about 10,000 years ago,
و هنا قبل حوالي 10,000 سنة
that two extraordinary inventions,
إختراعان رائعان
agriculture and urbanism, happened
الزراعة و التمدن , حدثا
roughly in the same place and at the same time.
معاً في ذات المكان ,و في ذات الوقت.
This is no accident,
هذا ليس مصادفة.
because agriculture and cities are bound together. They need each other.
لأن الزراعة و المدن مرتبطان معاً. هما يحتاجان إلى بعضهما.
Because it was discovery of grain
لأن إكتشاف الحبوب
by our ancient ancestors for the first time
عن طريق أجدادنا القدماء , للمرة الأولى,
that produced a food source that was large enough
التي أنتجت مصادر غذائية بكميات كافية
and stable enough to support permanent settlements.
و مستقرة لدعم المستوطنات الدائمة.
And if we look at what those settlements were like,
و إذا نظرنا إلى تلك المستوطنات
we see they were compact.
سنرى أنها كانت مركبة.
They were surrounded by productive farm land
كانت محاطة بمزارع إنتاجية
and dominated by large temple complexes
و يديرها مجمعات معبد كبير
like this one at Ur,
كهذه في مدينة أور
that were, in fact, effectively,
و التي كانت , حقيقةً, بكل كفاءة،
spiritualized, central food distribution centers.
مراكز روحانية و مراكز لتوزيع الغذاء
Because it was the temples that organized the harvest,
لأن المعابد كانت تقوم بتنظيم الحصاد,
gathered in the grain, offered it to the gods,
و التجمع عند الحبوب , و تقديمها للآلهة,
and then offered the grain that the gods didn't eat back to the people.
ثم تقديم الحبوب التي لم تأكلها الآلهة إلى الناس.
So, if you like,
لذلك, إن أحببتم, فإن
the whole spiritual and physical life of these cities
جميع مظاهر الحياة الروحانية و المادية لهذه المدن
was dominated by the grain and the harvest
سيطر عليها الحبوب و الحصاد
that sustained them.
اللذان حافظا عليهم.
And in fact, that's true of every ancient city.
في الواقع, هذه حقيقة في جميع المدن القديمة.
But of course not all of them were that small.
ولكن بالطبع لم يكونوا جميعا بهذا الصغر.
Famously, Rome had about a million citizens
معروف بأنه كان في روما مليون مواطن
by the first century A.D.
في العام الأول الميلادي.
So how did a city like this feed itself?
إذا كيف تقوم مدينة كهذه بإطعام نفسها؟
The answer is what I call "ancient food miles."
الإجابة هي ما أسميه "أميال الغذاء القديمة"
Basically, Rome had access to the sea,
روما تملك مدخلاً على البحر
which made it possible for it to import food from a very long way away.
ما جعلها تستطيع أن تستورد الغذاء من أماكن بعيدة جداً.
This is the only way it was possible to do this in the ancient world,
كانت هذه هي الطريقة الوحيدة الممكنة في العالم القديم
because it was very difficult to transport food over roads,
لأنه كان صعباً جداً نقل الغذاء عبر الطرق
which were rough.
التي كانت وعرة
And the food obviously went off very quickly.
و الغذاء بطبيعة الحال يتلف بسرعة كبيرة.
So Rome effectively waged war
لذلك فإن روما شنت حرباً بفعالية
on places like Carthage and Egypt
على مواقع مثل قرطاج و مصر
just to get its paws on their grain reserves.
فقط لتضع يديها على احتياطيهم من الحبوب
And, in fact, you could say that the expansion of the Empire
في الحقيقة, بإمكانكم القول بأن التوسع في الإمبراطورية
was really sort of one long, drawn out
كان نوعاً من متعة التسوق العسكري
militarized shopping spree, really.
البعيد الهادئ , حقيقةً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact -- I love the fact, I just have to mention this:
في الحقيقة - أحب هذه الحقيقة, لابد أن أذكر التالي:
Rome in fact used to import oysters from London,
روما حقيقةً [إستوردت المحار من بريطانيا]
at one stage. I think that's extraordinary.
في مرحلة. أعتقد أن هذا خارق.
So Rome shaped its hinterland
لذا فإن روما شكلت مناطقها النائية
through its appetite.
عن طريق شهيتها للطعام
But the interesting thing is that the other thing also
ولكن الشيء المثير للاهتمام هو الشيء الآخر
happened in the pre-industrial world.
الذي حدث في العالم ما قبل الصناعي.
If we look at a map of London in the 17th century,
إذا نظرنا إلى خريطةٍ لندن في القرن السابع عشر
we can see that its grain, which is coming in from the Thames,
بإمكاننا أن نرى بأن حبوبها التي تدخل من نهر التيمز
along the bottom of this map.
على طول أسفل الخريطة.
So the grain markets were to the south of the city.
لذا فإن أسواق الحبوب كانت في جنوب المدينة
And the roads leading up from them
و الطرق المؤدية منها
to Cheapside, which was the main market,
إلى شارع شيب سايد, الذي كان السوق المركزي,
were also grain markets.
كانت أيضاً أسواق للحبوب
And if you look at the name of one of those streets,
و إذا نظرتم إلى اسم واحد من هذه الطرق
Bread Street, you can tell
شارع الخبز , بإمكانكم أن تعلم
what was going on there 300 years ago.
ماذا كان يحدث هناك قبل 300 سنة.
And the same of course was true for fish.
و طبعاً هذا ينطبق أيضاً على السمك
Fish was, of course, coming in by river as well. Same thing.
السمك كان يدخل عبر النهر أيضاً
And of course Billingsgate, famously, was London's fish market,
و بالطبع فإن بيلينغس جيت ,المعروف, كان سوق السمك في لندن,
operating on-site here until the mid-1980s.
استمر العمل فبه حتى منتصف الثمانينات.
Which is extraordinary, really, when you think about it.
إنه شيء رائع ,حقاً, عندما تتخيله.
Everybody else was wandering around
الجميع كانوا يتجولون
with mobile phones that looked like bricks
و معهم هواتف نقالة تشبه الطوب,
and sort of smelly fish happening down on the port.
و نوع من الأسماك ذات رائحة في الميناء
This is another thing about food in cities:
شيء آخر عن الغذاء في المدن:
Once its roots into the city are established,
ما إن يتم إنشاء جذورها في المدينة,
they very rarely move.
فإنها نادراً ما تنتقل.
Meat is a very different story
اللحم قصة مختلفة تماماً
because, of course, animals could walk into the city.
لأن الحيوانات تستطيع السير إلى المدينة.
So much of London's meat
كمية كبيرة من لحوم لندن
was coming from the northwest,
كانت تأتي من الشمال الغربي.
from Scotland and Wales.
من اسكتلاندا و ويلز
So it was coming in, and arriving at the city at the northwest,
لذا فقد كانت تدخل و تصل إلى شمال غرب المدينة,
which is why Smithfield,
و لذلك فإن سميث فيلد,
London's very famous meat market, was located up there.
وهو سوق لحوم مشهور جداً, كان يقع هناك في الأعلى
Poultry was coming in from East Anglia and so on, to the northeast.
الدواجن كانت تأتي من أنجيليا الشرقية و غيرها إلى الشمال الشرقي.
I feel a bit like a weather woman doing this. Anyway,
أشعر و كأنني كمذيعة الطقس و أفعل هكذا. على كل حال.
and so the birds were coming in
و كذلك الطيور كانت تدخل
with their feet protected with little canvas shoes.
و أرجلها محمية بحذاء قماشي خفيف
And then when they hit the eastern end
و عندما تضرب الطرف الشرقي
of Cheapside, that's where they were sold,
من شيب سايد, تُباع هناك.
which is why it's called Poultry.
وهذا سبب تسميتها الإنجليزية وتعني التدلي
And, in fact, if you look at the map of any city
و إذا نظرتم إلى خريطة أية مدينة
built before the industrial age,
بُنيت قبل عصر الصناعة,
you can trace food coming in to it.
فإنه بإمكانكم تتبع الغذاء الداخل إليها.
You can actually see how it was physically shaped by food,
بإمكانكم ملاحظة كيف تشكلت بنية المدينة عن طريق الغذاء,
both by reading the names of the streets, which give you a lot of clues.
بقراءة أسماء الشوارع التي تعطيكم الكثير من المعلومات.
Friday Street, in a previous life,
شارع يوم الجمعة, في فترة سابقة,
is where you went to buy your fish on a Friday.
هو المكان الذي تذهب إليه يوم الجمعة لشراء السمك.
But also you have to imagine it full of food.
و عليك أيضاً أن تتخيله مليء بالأغذية.
Because the streets and the public spaces
لأن الشوارع و الساحات العامة
were the only places where food was bought and sold.
هي الأماكن الوحيدة التي يباع فيها الغذاء و يشترى.
And if we look at an image of Smithfield in 1830
و إذا نظرنا إلى صورة لسميث فيلد سنة 1830
you can see that it would have been very difficult to live in a city like this
بإمكانكم ملاحظة أنه من الصعب جداً العيش في مدينة كهذه
and be unaware of where your food came from.
و أن لا تعرف من أين أتى غذاؤك
In fact, if you were having Sunday lunch,
في الحقيقة, إذا كنت تتناول غداء يوم الأحد,
the chances were it was mooing or bleating outside your window
فان الفرص هي أن تكون تخور أو تثغو خارج نافذتك
about three days earlier.
قبل حوالي ثلاثة أيام
So this was obviously an organic city,
لذلك فإنه من الواضح أنها مدينة عضوية,
part of an organic cycle.
جزء من دورة عضوية.
And then 10 years later everything changed.
ثم بعد 10 سنوات كل شيء تغير
This is an image of the Great Western in 1840.
هذه صورة لسكة الحديد الغربية العظيمة سنة 1840
And as you can see, some of the earliest train passengers
و كما ترون, بعض أوائل ركاب القطار
were pigs and sheep.
كانوا خنازير و خراف
So all of a sudden, these animals are no longer walking into market.
إذا فجأةً هذه الحيوانات لم تعد تمشي إلى السوق
They're being slaughtered out of sight and mind,
بل تُذبح بعيداً عن الأنظار
somewhere in the countryside.
في مكان ما في الأرياف.
And they're coming into the city by rail.
و تدخل المدينة عن طريق السكة الحديدية
And this changes everything.
و هذا يغير كل شيء.
To start off with, it makes it possible
لنبدأ بها، للمرة الأولى
for the first time to grow cities,
أصبح بإمكان المدن النمو
really any size and shape, in any place.
بأي مساحة و شكل , في أي مكان.
Cities used to be constrained by geography;
كانت المدن مقيدة بالجغرافيا:
they used to have to get their food through very difficult physical means.
كانت مضطرةً أن تحصل على غذائها بوسائل مادية صعبة.
All of a sudden they are effectively emancipated from geography.
و فجأةً , تحررت من الجغرافيا.
And as you can see from these maps of London,
و كما ترون من هذه الخرائط للندن.
in the 90 years after the trains came,
خلال ال90 عاماً بعد مجيء القطارات.
it goes from being a little blob that was quite easy to feed
إنتقلت المدن من نقطة صغيرة من السهل إطعامها
by animals coming in on foot, and so on,
عن طريق الحيوانات الداخلة سيراً على الأقدام,
to a large splurge,
إلى مفاخر عظيمة,
that would be very, very difficult to feed with anybody on foot,
والتي من الصعب جداً جداً إطعامها بما يسير على الأقدام
either animals or people.
سواءاً كان من جانب الحيوانات أو الناس.
And of course that was just the beginning. After the trains came cars,
و بالطبع كانت هذه هي البداية فقط. فبعد القطارات جاءت السيارات.
and really this marks the end of this process.
و كانت تلك هي نهاية هذه العملية.
It's the final emancipation of the city
إنها آخر تحرر للمدينة
from any apparent relationship with nature at all.
من أية علاقة واضحة مع الطبيعة.
And this is the kind of city that's devoid of smell,
و هذا هو نوع المدينة الخالية من الرائحة,
devoid of mess, certainly devoid of people,
و خالية من الفوضى, و طبعاً خالية من الناس.
because nobody would have dreamed of walking in such a landscape.
لأنه لا أحد حلم بأن يسير في هذه المناطق الطبيعية.
In fact, what they did to get food was they got in their cars,
لكي يحصلوا على الغذاء, فإنهم يركبون سياراتهم
drove to a box somewhere on the outskirts,
و يقودونها إلى محل في مكان ما في الضواحي
came back with a week's worth of shopping,
و يعودون بمشتريات لأسبوع.
and wondered what on earth to do with it.
و يتساءلون ماذا سنفعل بها.
And this really is the moment when our relationship,
و هذه هي اللحظة التي فيها علاقتنا
both with food and cities, changes completely.
بالغذاء و المدن معاً قد تغيرت.
Here we have food -- that used to be the center,
هنا لدينا الغذاء -- الذي كان المركز
the social core of the city -- at the periphery.
و الجوهر الإجتماعي للمدينة -- على المحيط
It used to be a social event, buying and selling food.
كان بيع و شراء الغذاء حدث إجتماعي
Now it's anonymous.
الآن هو مجهول.
We used to cook; now we just add water,
كنا نطبخ. الآن نحن فقط نضيف الماء
or a little bit of an egg if you're making a cake or something.
أو شيء من بيضة إذا كنا نحضر كعكاً أو شيئاً من ذلك.
We don't smell food to see if it's okay to eat.
لا نشم الغذاء لنرى هل يصلح للأكل.
We just read the back of a label on a packet.
فقط نقرأ خلف الملصق على العلبة.
And we don't value food. We don't trust it.
و نحن لا نقدر الغذاء. لا نثق به.
So instead of trusting it, we fear it.
و بدلاً من أن نثق به نخاف منه.
And instead of valuing it, we throw it away.
و بدلاً من تقديره نبدده.
One of the great ironies of modern food systems
واحدة من أكبر مفارقات أنظمة الغذاء الحديثة
is that they've made the very thing they promised
أنها حققت الشيء الحقيقي الذي وعدت به
to make easier much harder.
وهو جعل السهل أصعب
By making it possible to build cities anywhere and any place,
بإتاحة بناء المدن في أي مكان
they've actually distanced us from our most important relationship,
هي فعليا أبعدتنا عن أهم علاقة
which is that of us and nature.
و هي نحن و الطبيعة.
And also they've made us dependent on systems that only they can deliver,
و هي أيضاً جعلتنا نعتمد على الأنظمة التي يستطيعون توصيلها فقط
that, as we've seen, are unsustainable.
و هي كما رأينا غير دائمة.
So what are we going to do about that?
إذاً ماذا سنفعل بذلك؟
It's not a new question.
هذا ليس سؤال جديد
500 years ago it's what Thomas More was asking himself.
قبل 500 عام سأل توماس مور نفسه هذا السؤال.
This is the frontispiece of his book "Utopia."
هذه واجهة كتابه "المدينة الفاضلة"
And it was a series of semi-independent city-states,
و كان سلسلة من دول مدن شبه مستقلة
if that sounds remotely familiar,
إذا كان هذا مألوفاً
a day's walk from one another where everyone was basically farming-mad,
مسيرة يوم من دولة إلى أخرى حيث أن الجميع مهوسين بالزراعة
and grew vegetables in their back gardens,
و يزرعون الخضروات في حدائقهم الخلفية
and ate communal meals together, and so on.
و يأكلون وجبات الطعام معاً وغيرها
And I think you could argue that
و أظن أنه بإمكانكم القول بأن
food is a fundamental ordering principle of Utopia,
الغذاء هو مبدأ أساسي في المدينة الفاضلة
even though More never framed it that way.
حتى لو أن مور لم يؤطره بهذا الشكل.
And here is another very famous "Utopian" vision,
و هذه رؤية أخرى معروفة للمدينة الفاضلة
that of Ebenezer Howard, "The Garden City."
ل إبنيزر هوارد, "المدينة الحدائقية"
Same idea: series of semi-independent city-states,
الفكرة ذاتها. مجموعة من دول مدن شبه مستقلة
little blobs of metropolitan stuff with arable land around,
نقاط صغيرة من ممتلكات العاصمة محاطة بأراضي صالحة للزراعة
joined to one another by railway.
مرتبطة ببعضها بواسطة سكة حديدية.
And again, food could be said to be
و أيضاً يمكن القول بأن الغذاء
the ordering principle of his vision.
هو المبدأ الأساسي لهذه الرؤية.
It even got built, but nothing to do with
لقد بُنيت و لكن لا شيء فُعل
this vision that Howard had.
بهذه الرؤية الخاصة بهوارد.
And that is the problem with these Utopian ideas,
و المشكلة المتعلقة بأفكار المدينة الفاضلة
that they are Utopian.
أنها مثالية.
Utopia was actually a word that Thomas Moore used deliberately.
الفاضلة هي كلمة تعمد توماس مور إستخدامها.
It was a kind of joke, because it's got a double derivation from the Greek.
كانت نوعاً من الدعابة. لأن لها إشتقاقين من اليونانية.
It can either mean a good place, or no place.
يمكن أن تعني مكان جيد أو لا مكان.
Because it's an ideal. It's an imaginary thing. We can't have it.
لأنها مثالية. لذا فهي خيالية. لا يمكن الحصول عليها.
And I think, as a conceptual tool
و أظن, أنه كوسيلة تصور
for thinking about the very deep problem of human dwelling,
لمشكلة سكن الإنسان العميقة
that makes it not much use.
يجعلها غير مستعملة
So I've come up with an alternative,
لذا أتيت ببديل
which is Sitopia, from the ancient Greek,
هو سيتوبيا , من اليونانية القديمة
"sitos" for food, and "topos" for place.
سيتو = غذاء, و توبيا = مكان
I believe we already live in Sitopia.
أنا أعتقد بأننا نعيش في سيتوبيا
We live in a world shaped by food,
نحن نعيش في عالم يُشكله الغذاء
and if we realize that, we can use food as a really powerful tool --
و لو آمنّا بأننا نستطيع أن نستخدم الغذاء كأداة فعالة --
a conceptual tool, design tool, to shape the world differently.
أداة مفاهيم, أداة تخطيط, لتغيير شكل العالم.
So if we were to do that, what might Sitopia look like?
إذا كنّا نريد ذلك كيف سيكون شكل سيتوبيا؟
Well I think it looks a bit like this.
حسناً أظن أنه يشبه هذا
I have to use this slide. It's just the look on the face of the dog.
أنا مضطرة لاستخدام هذه الشريحة. إنها فقط النظرة على وجه الكلب.
But anyway, this is -- (Laughter)
بالمناسبة , هذا --(ضحك)
it's food at the center of life,
هذا الغذاء هو محور الحياة
at the center of family life, being celebrated,
محور حياة العائلة, إذا كانت تحتفل,
being enjoyed, people taking time for it.
إذا كانت تستمتع, الناس يعطون وقتاً له.
This is where food should be in our society.
هنا حيث يجب أن يكون الغذاء في مجتمعنا.
But you can't have scenes like this unless you have people like this.
ولكن لايمكنكم الحصول على مشاهد كهذه إن لم يكن لديكم أشخاص كهؤلاء.
By the way, these can be men as well.
بالمناسبة, هؤلاء يمكن أن يكونوا رجالاً أيضاً.
It's people who think about food,
أشخاص يفكرون بالغذاء
who think ahead, who plan,
ينظرون للمستقبل , يخططون
who can stare at a pile of raw vegetables
بإمكانهم التحديق في كومة من الخضروات
and actually recognize them.
و تمييزها.
We need these people. We're part of a network.
نحن بحاجة إلى هؤلاء. نحن جزء من شبكة.
Because without these kinds of people we can't have places like this.
لأنه بدون هؤلاء لن يكون عندنا أماكن كهذه
Here, I deliberately chose this because it is a man buying a vegetable.
هنا تعمدت أن أختار هذه لأنه رجل يشتري خضروات.
But networks, markets where food is being grown locally.
ولكن الشبكات, وهي الأسواق التي يُنتج فيها الغذاء محلياً
It's common. It's fresh.
إنها عامة و طازجة
It's part of the social life of the city.
إنها جزء من الحياة الإجتماعية للمدينة.
Because without that, you can't have this kind of place,
لأنه بدونها لن يكون عندك مثل هذا المكان,
food that is grown locally and also is part of the landscape,
غذاء يُنتج محلياً و أيضاً جزء من المشهد الطبيعي.
and is not just a zero-sum commodity
و ليس سلعة زهيدة
off in some unseen hell-hole.
بعيدة في حفرة جحيم لا تُرى.
Cows with a view.
أبقار في مشهد جميل
Steaming piles of humus.
تبخير أكوام الدبال
This is basically bringing the whole thing together.
هذا يشكل صورة كاملة.
And this is a community project
هذا مشروع جماعي
I visited recently in Toronto.
زرت حديثاً تورونتو
It's a greenhouse, where kids get told
إنها بيت أخضر, حيث الأطفال يتعلمون
all about food and growing their own food.
كل ما يخص الغذاء و إنتاج غذائهم.
Here is a plant called Kevin, or maybe it's a
هذه نبتة اسمها كيفن, أو ربما هي
plant belonging to a kid called Kevin. I don't know.
نبتة لطفل إسمه كيفن, لا أعلم.
But anyway, these kinds of projects
ولكن على كل حال, إن هذا النوع من المشاريع
that are trying to reconnect us with nature is extremely important.
التي تحاول إعادة ربطنا بالطبيعة مهمة جداً
So Sitopia, for me, is really a way of seeing.
لذلك سيتوبيا بالنسبة لي هي طريقة نظر.
It's basically recognizing that Sitopia
إنها في الأساس الإعتراف بأن سيتوبيا
already exists in little pockets everywhere.
موجودة مسبقاً في جيوب صغيرة في كل مكان.
The trick is to join them up,
البراعة هي في جمعها معاً
to use food as a way of seeing.
لاستخدام الغذاء كطريقة نظر
And if we do that, we're going to stop seeing cities
و لو فعلنا ذلك سنتوقف عن رؤية المدن
as big, metropolitan, unproductive blobs, like this.
كعواصم كبيرة غير منتجة كهذه
We're going to see them more like this,
سنستطيع أن نراهم كهذه
as part of the productive, organic framework
كجزء من النظام العضوي المنتج
of which they are inevitably a part,
الذي هم حتماً جزء منه
symbiotically connected.
في ارتباط عضوي
But of course, that's not a great image either,
ولكن بالطبع هذه ليست صورة عظيمة
because we need not to be producing food like this anymore.
لأننا يجب أن لاننتج غذاءاً كهذا.
We need to be thinking more about permaculture,
علينا أن نفكر في الزراعة و الثقافة الثابتتين
which is why I think this image just
لذلك فهذه الصورة
sums up for me the kind of thinking we need to be doing.
تشكل لدي نوع التفكير الذي يجب أن نقوم به
It's a re-conceptualization
إنها إعادة تصور
of the way food shapes our lives.
للطريقة التي يشكل فيها الغذاء حياتنا
The best image I know of this is from 650 years ago.
أفضل صورة أعرفها لها هي من قبل 650 عاماً
It's Ambrogio Lorenzetti's "Allegory of Good Government."
إنها رمز الحكومة الخيره لـ أمبروجيو لورينزيت
It's about the relationship between the city and the countryside.
إنها عن العلاقة بين المدينة و الريف.
And I think the message of this is very clear.
و أعتقد بأن الرسالة منها واضحة جداً
If the city looks after the country,
إذا كانت المدينة تعتني بالريف
the country will look after the city.
سيعتني الريف بالمدينة
And I want us to ask now,
و أريد منّا أن نسأل الآن
what would Ambrogio Lorenzetti paint
ماذا سيرسم أمبروجيو لورينزيت
if he painted this image today?
لو أراد أن يرسم الآن.
What would an allegory of good government look like today?
ماذا سيكون رمز الحكومة الخيره اليوم؟
Because I think it's an urgent question.
لأنه باعتقادي سؤال ملح
It's one we have to ask,
إنه سؤال يجب أن نسأله
and we have to start answering.
و علينا أن نبدأ بالإجابة عنه
We know we are what we eat.
نحن نعلم بأننا نحن ما نأكل
We need to realize that the world is also what we eat.
علينا أن نعترف بأن العالم أيضاً هو ما يأكله.
But if we take that idea, we can use food
لكن إذا إستعنّا بهذه الفكرة بإمكننا أن نستخدم الغذاء
as a really powerful tool to shape the world better.
كوسيلة فعّالة لتشكيل العالم بشكل أفضل
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)